[Music]
hey folks welcome back to the Dark Horse
podcast our 16th livestream the Q & A
section where we will answer as many of
your super chat questions as we can get
to so we had a glitch in the downloading
of the questions this time and so during
the break Zack and I were working
furiously to collect them but it is
possible that we missed some and we
never get to all of them but he we tried
to get all of the ones above a certain
dollar level apologies if we missed it
if you would email the Dark Horse
moderator which i think is at Dark Horse
dot moderator at gmail.com I'm not I
know with your question if if at the end
of this we didn't get to it we will
prioritize it was the certain level
we'll prioritize it for next time yes
and from the perspective of preventing
this collapse on future live streams
please when you upload questions make
sure the filaments and the wire have
been tightly twisted together and don't
let the pressure get above 30 psi thank
you thank you
okay cliff high with a large a large
donation Thank You cliff sense consider
personal consciousness where in the body
do you understand it to be bound where
do you feel it to be bound and where do
you think it to be bound I know but what
your thoughts are these informed by
psychedelic experience do you know the
biological mechanism of the binding well
I thought I understood the question
until the last question in the sequence
the question with regard to the
biological mechanism of the bio the
binding and the binding seems like
something very precise and it could
refer to the binding of the
neurotransmitter mimic in a psychedelic
anthea Jim but I don't know if that's
what it's getting at I would say
the question is informed by psychedelic
experience that's one thing I think is
true you think it's immediately informed
by second are necessarily it seems quite
quite clear headed I think although I'm
not sure I think there's a premise here
that we might disagree with if I could
quite understand what the premises but
I'm not sure I know what it is yeah I
suspect that much to the annoyance of
all sorts of people that consciousness
individual consciousness is a feature of
the mind the mind being what the brain
does and therefore we're in the brain
does that mean that there's nothing to
thinking about it in any other way
probably not but yeah from the
perspective of what kinds of damage you
might get that would interfere with your
consciousness I suspect it is localized
in that way and you know I would say
localized and with ever less strength
potentially the less dense you are with
regard to nerves so you know the CNS the
central nervous system which includes
much as the brain but the spinal cord
might be the the core area and there are
things that the motor neurons and
sensory neurons may be doing and the
inter neurons that it could be
transmitting aspects of consciousness
that we don't understand I'm not going
to ask you how dense you think I am with
the neurons or anything else but I will
say for cliff and anybody else who's
interested in our thinking on
consciousness what we have argued is
that individual consciousness is a
secondary adaptation that follows from
the consciousness that exists between
individuals and the consciousness that
exists between individuals is not
localized in the same way in the mind
that's where the model would take place
but the fact that it is an emergent
property between two people means that
it is in effect not localized in the
same sense so I don't know if that
answers your question
cliff but I I hope it shed some light
next question do you think the truth
scales if so might the prints with what
certain is Laszlo's hierarchy I think
he's referring to Maslow's hierarchy of
needs distinguishing noble and common
needs or people be a good barometer for
one to govern oneself and Mike
Peterson's 12 rules be a rubric for
government to follow and governing a
population Nate who also donated a fair
bit has packed a lot into this question
let me just say it again so that it's I
think there's three questions there's
there's a question and two possible
answers here do you think truth scales
if we think the answer is yes
Nate posits that perhaps the prince
which is Machiavelli's famous book in
which the noble versus the common
descriptor that Machiavelli uses might
be mapped on to Laszlo's Maslow's
hierarchy even the aides be a good
barometer for self-governance and might
Petersons 12 roles be a good model for
government governance that's how I
understand the question but it's there's
a lot more to be impact there some
truths scale at least to some extent
through any true scale infinitely hard
to say I'm concerned about anything like
trying to take something like The Prince
and yes it might be better if your
Machiavellian tendencies unfolded
internal to you as an individual it's
probably a closer approximation of
something decent
but the problem is you might well end up
deferring to some entirely somatic view
of life where you effectively took that
as a license for hedonism which I don't
think is a very good use of a life so no
I wouldn't advocate it as a principle
maybe the harm you do is to yourself
rather than to others so it's not so
onerous but but anyway I'm not sure
about it and that doesn't strike me that
Peterson's 12 rules are scaled properly
for for the governance of populations I
don't use their intent and I think
quite precisely I've read the book and I
found it quite excellent
but it is specifically about how
individuals should act I feel like it is
it is far better in that first position
of a good barometer for how to govern
oneself or at least how to start
governing oneself before you figure out
how you may be different from your
neighbors but that it doesn't seem
really to be a rubric for a population
level analysis and I think I think you
would agree with that although I'd be
curious to have that conversation I
suspect it and then with regard to the
first part of the question which you
already addressed you think truth scales
I would say maybe that patterns and
ideas may scale so you know selection
for instance natural selection exists at
all of these different levels and across
domains even in non biological domains
and so that is a kind of scaling whereas
you know it's it depends on what kind of
truth were talking about and that sounds
like a wishy-washy trying to get out of
the question but some truths will scale
maybe never infinitely but some truths
are completely hyper local to the space
and time in which they exist yeah I mean
I think you've done a good job of
nailing the most likely candidate which
would be that the things that accumulate
in the universe will be patterns that
come into existence frequently that are
similar to each other when they do so
they're recognized as a category that
are durable upon arrival and that
capture limited substances or other
properties of the universe such that
they effectively out-compete other
things that might contain them so that's
a that's the underlying substrata on
which Darwinism floats and it applies to
all sorts of things that have nothing to
do with biology and so if we just apply
it to patterns yes that's the most
likely thing to apply at every scale in
the universe but then again what do we
do you know it tops out at the universe
I think maybe not all right all right
next question
from Raphael with gatekeeping and
academia and the crisis happening
together how do and the current pandemic
crisis presumably how do graduate
students live and participate what to do
if advisors are gatekeepers advice if
you can't find positions because of
gatekeepers and theoretical parts of
science and math oh man this is a good
and clearly heartfelt and difficult
question I think the best we can do is
probably we feel for you and it's a
really terrible situation but the way
limited resources are allocated in
science puts people in charge many of
whom are not worthy of that kind of
responsibility and we've seen it up
close and many people who might steer us
in a much better direction if they were
liberated to do so are constrained by
the fact that they are effectively
forced to fall on their swords if they
go in a direction that does not please
the hierarchy above them so this is a
puzzle that needs solving and there's
nothing riding on it but the game yeah
very much so I guess I mean we can talk
about this a little bit a little bit
more this doesn't get so much to how you
find positions after you've gotten a
degree how do you find positions in
academia after you've gotten a degree
which is its own set of problems but
when you're actually in graduate school
and if you have an ability to choose
between advisers and see that some seem
to be more of the gatekeeping type and
some less you you can imagine that it's
actually it would make a lot of sense
from a self-interest position to be a
gatekeeper as an academic and in fact
whole departments tend to be of the sort
of gatekeeping mindset or not and even
in those departments that allow graduate
students more freedom to choose their
own questions as opposed to slot into a
space in the lab and ask a question
that's handed to you even in those
departments that tend towards the more
freedom for graduate students to ask the
questions and you know sink or swim
which is certainly the the way that
Michigan's biology department was when
we were there even there you'll find
of there would be advisors some of the
faculty being more gatekeeping and so
really finding a place where you know
choosing an advisor who has students who
are asking all range of questions who
engages in conversation in which
disagreement happens and in which the
entire lab is not dependent on one or
two or a longitudinal string of large
grants which are going to be basically
you're going to get a reversion to the
mean you're going to get more and more
Orthodoxy if you're reliant on the big
money coming in from the government
grants that require the same kinds of
results has always been coming in so you
know find someone who is doing more
eclectic heterodox research but of
course those people themselves are
becoming harder and harder to find you
know we both all three of the advisors
whom we had who you mentioned in the
last hour Bob Trevor's dick Alexander
and Arnold Kluge were all of those
things they were they were heterodox and
encouraging you know they they wouldn't
none of them ever would have wanted
students to simply slot into their own
research they would have found that
absurd and anathema and yet it is the
common thing for graduate advisors
especially at least in many aspects of
stem I know less about the other parts
of the Academy yeah one thing you could
do is you could consider cryogenics you
could have yourself frozen and then see
if it's any better in a hundred years
you're drinking alcohol no I'm not
drinking anything brought out the
darkness in my mood happened next
question could very different or mildly
different back coronavirus variants
evolve in different bat species for
instance Ranelagh food sources tear
opponents who live in the same ecosystem
or cave of course the very fact that you
asked the question means you must
understand the basis on which it would
happen you know there's always a
question about what the the gap between
species means about the likelihood of it
finding its way across but yeah Randall
ofits versus Terra POTUS is a pretty big
gap it's kind of as big a gap as you get
within bats
so this is the the I believe the
expected distance between these two has
shrunk on the basis that Ryan elephants
have been moved towards tarapoto yeah
yeah actually uh yeah not as far as it
would seem about as far as it would seem
given that Ryan elephants are what we
call Micro bats and Terra poets or mega
bats
there's that new framing the young toe
versus the MPO versus yang Dakar opt I
don't remember what the prefixes are
they've used but now yeah they've got
the right a little bit sand the Tara
poets which are the big fruit bats in
the same group though yes they those
people do they bat gate keepers final
edge and gate keepers now is there an
evolutionary reason of why women have
the ability to achieve multiple orgasms
thank you
[Laughter]
sure of course circus of course there is
but that's that's but then what well yes
there is it's complex and it's rated in
there's variation how much people
experience it this is not my first time
at the rodeo I must tell you do you
remember when we were teaching together
some years ago and a very nice
intelligent young woman in our class
asked me to explain female orgasm and
the evolution of lady bits during a
lecture so I learned in that in that
insist is that the phrase she used
yes that lady bit that was the phrase
and it was very important that I not
become embarrassed at that moment which
I didn't do remember this so there is
one thing that must govern your actions
should you ever be asked a question like
this
should you be male or I guess a gay
female which is that the answer you
deliver must leave people with the
impression they don't have to understand
your answer but they must be left with
the impression that you are something of
an expert about female orgasm that is
what they should walk away with a
question from so to that end let me just
say that I'm glad I'm what do you answer
this one
so female orgasm is not obvious which is
why people ask
about it the fact is females by the
nature of being the limiting sex have a
very easy time coming by gambits gametes
if that's what they need and so why have
this powerful reward system accompany
various sexual acts and the answer I am
almost certain has to do with the nature
of human pair-bonding and the fact that
the male orgasm has been borrowed by
selection appended to two females
slightly differently but appended to
females to facilitate a kind of sexual
bonding that results in an increase in
fitness so in other words females being
rewarded by sex in this very direct and
powerful way behave in a fashion that is
more likely to result in successful
reproduction that is to say offspring
that gilliam themselves to reproduce and
my argument would be that that is
basically to induce females to engage in
behavior that is rewarding to male such
that they stick around that's some level
I agree with all that but I don't think
it addresses the question you didn't
have to I just had to leave the
impression that I knew a lot about it
yeah but I I think as much as that was
actually a great answer to the question
of his female orgasm adaptive yeah right
but this question is specifically about
multiple orgasms which is the part of
the question where I'm like I don't know
actually what to say here yes adaptive
but but why and I don't have anything in
particular on that um for one thing this
is an incentive to females but it is
also an incentive to males in other
words to the extent that I mean male
orgasm and female orgasm are very
different in the sense that male orgasm
rather famously changes one's frame of
mind almost instantaneously the fact
that it doesn't do that for women and
I'm not saying it doesn't do it at all
but the fact that there could
potentially be other orgasms down the
line keeps male attention focused and
again the pole
is going to be the bond is actually
vital to the fitness of both parties and
therefore each one is structured to
deliver the other what is needed in
order to keep them engaged okay that's
good keeps keeps the mill focused twenty
forty years ago that would have been
described simply as mate guarding but it
does the same trick it effectively keeps
you keeps you close potentially and and
ready to go forward to potentially even
non sexual behavior but it can go to
sexual again
yeah and for those of you interested in
this style of question I would just
simply point out there are a whole set
of features of human sex and sexuality
that are utterly unique and some of them
that are mostly unique having sex when
not fertile female orgasm concealment of
ovulation persistence of female breasts
enlarged when not feeding offspring all
of these things are part of a very
sexually unique species and the puzzle
pieces don't fit together in a way and
it's completely obvious why we're built
this way but it is a set of questions
that is well worth spending some time
thinking about and don't treat sex
trivially all right dad mandated
lockdowns curtail our liberties and
destroy wealth and livelihood on a grand
scale
advocates for lock down bear the burden
of proof to show that a larger
catastrophe is likely has that burden
been met there's an assumption on the
question that advocates for lock down
bear the burden of proof and it's this
this I think would benefit from us being
able to have a back and forth with the
person who asked that question I can't
even see the name of that person right
now because of the thing that happened
between the two live streams you know
what a larger catastrophe being likely
what would be the burden you know what
how would you know likely where would
you set the bar for likelihood or larger
and or larger given that lockdown if
it's successful reveal not as large a
catastrophe as anyone was predicting how
do you measure success
of these are real concerns and I think I
mean I think the big the big place here
that I at least and I think you Brett
would probably at least begin
disagreeing with the questioner is that
advocates bear the burden of proof to
show hmm actually no I'm not sure that's
that's the issue it's there's some tools
you need to unpack this there's the
question of ex ante versus ex post in
other words there's you have to figure
out what we would expect going forward
where we don't know what happened versus
what will have happened after we've been
through it so here we are choosing one
of two paths and they will have
different outcomes so there's an
expectation of what the path will bring
and then there's the reality of what it
does bring and those two things the ex
post is not so interesting because we're
making this Asian's ex ante there's a
question about precaution so obviously
there are costs both ways and obviously
we don't end driving just because it
would save lives
we decide that a certain number of lives
we're willing to lose in order to retain
driving so by analogy certainly there is
a certain number of lives that we would
be willing to lose not to have to go on
lockdown but presumably that number is
something we can discuss and that the
tens of thousands of deaths that we look
like that we appear to be staring at and
there is substantial data now about what
results from the relaxation of lockdowns
what has resulted in places where the
lock downs have not occurred or have
been less stringent so we do have a lot
of information and the information that
I have seen so far does suggest that
there is substandard
we don't yet know what's going to happen
down the road we are limiting the number
of individuals in which this virus gets
to evolutionarily
bearment we may be saving ourselves an
indefinitely large amount down the road
by paying the cost upfront of lockdown
now I can't say for sure that that's
happening but it does need to be in the
conversation about whether or not to do
this can we slow this thing down by
giving it less territory in which to
experiment long enough that we can get
ahead of it what happens if this thing
is recurrent and comes back to people
who've been sick again and again over
their lives if you knew that to be the
case you would understand that it was
much more important that we prevent
people from getting sick because it's
not like most of these people get sick
and they get better they get sick and
then maybe they get sick again and they
keep spreading it now I'm not saying
that that's happening I think it's
probably not happening but until we know
for sure that it's not happening it
justifies extra caution and I think a
lot of these things that we're looking
at are the same structure where the
unknowns are still substantial and at
the moment we have this thing somewhat
limited we could have done a lot better
if we've gotten on earlier and had been
more stringent we could have potentially
stamped it out in a matter of weeks if
we had gone at it aggressively and
rapidly instead it took us long enough
that it escaped the possibility so those
are the things we're playing with and I
think when you hear from those of us who
think that stringent measures are
necessary these are some of the
parameters we're talking about that's
great
what are your leading hypotheses on the
mechanism of consciousness that is the
hard problem of consciousness please
discuss your theory with Sam and Annika
Harris and is consciousness binary on or
off or is it made of parts or layers I'm
serious but he's included an emoji
oh god that's confusing well I think I
think we can direct people to - what
we've written that's not published yet
but also the talk that we gave at
Princeton a couple weeks ago now it's
available online at the James Madison
program site and
it's so that bat will get at the second
third of the question which is his
conscious binary or is it made of parts
and layers and I I suspect although I
don't know if we've exactly talked about
this that there is that by anyway I
imagine that there is a sort of a moment
of illuminating right but then beyond
that it's very much it very much scales
with the complexity of the brain and the
social system and the developmental
history and the length of childhood and
a number of generations living together
in all of this so that it's not it's not
binary and that you have it or you don't
except yes probably most organisms don't
at all but then the degree to which you
can be conscious is largely explanatory
in terms of whether or not you end up
being able to for instance have
conversations like this and then the
mechanism is a different one and maybe
we already sort of covered it with the
first question yeah I'd say we are not
believers that there is a hard problem
the hard problem is taken to have two
parts one is what's it for or the other
is how does it work what's it for seems
more tractable and our answer involves
consciousness being a necessary layer
constructed in the mind in order to
understand what another mind is saying
thinking feeling etc and so there's an
emergent consciousness between two
individuals that is necessary for them
to plug their minds into each other in
order to parallel process a problem
which results in higher quality answers
than the two Minds working separately
would be able to accomplish how does it
work obviously that's a technically
tougher issue but is it so tough then
it's not going to yield two techniques
that study neurological phenomena I
don't see the slightest bit of evidence
for that
it's a phenomenon of the brain and it's
a marvelous one is it you know it's not
gonna be a threshold right we can define
a threshold and we can say is this
animal across it or not but the fact is
even in your own consciousness you can
feel that there are things of which you
are highly conscious things of which you
are not conscious at all and things that
hover somewhere in between and that you
can push that boundary around at will by
concentrating on things or ignoring them
whatever you do so there's no reason to
expect that that's not an analog for the
way this is distributed in nature but
you would argue would you not that there
are certainly organisms that have no
consciousness oh yeah so that does
suggest a threshold of sorts but but not
one beyond which it's really interesting
to talk about do you have it do you not
like there's some level of consciousness
and it's highly variable within space
and time both at the micro and macro
level I mean sort of seems to me like
you know vascularization or something
mmm yep there gonna be some entities
without any and then there's gonna be
every gradation up to the maximum amount
and that maximum amount is probably not
a theoretical maximum is just what we
happen to have the maximum of and so my
guess is consciousness is like that and
you know a spruce tree isn't gonna have
any and you know a spider probably
doesn't have any and probably an octopus
doesn't have any smart as it is a cat
has a bit a dog has a lot you know and
people have the kind of consciousness
you get when it comes packaged with
linguistic capacity which is you know
leaps and bounds beyond anything else
good ok questions from echo the
rationality rules video that you
referenced Brett said that homeopathy is
literally false metaphorically true
sounds conclusion driven can you give
your take on homeopathy and how can its
mechanism be compared to vaccines and it
Kopacz a lot into her questions wait a
second I am Not sure that I interpreted
the video to say the same thing was
homeopathy not described as placebo like
in that video and in that video he did I
don't think I've seen the video yeah so
he unpacked metaphorical truth and he
goes through the Peterson Harris debates
and you know I was very pleased that he
said I had come closest to rescuing the
baby from the bath water with
metaphorical truth anyway his point was
and actually I was thinking about doing
a response his point was Brett seems to
speak very carefully
about behaving as if something is true
rather than believing that it is true
because he claims I am avoiding the trap
that would be set for me with placebos
now placebos are a topic that is
absolutely deserving of an exploration
it's not what you think it is but
nonetheless I liked his conjecture I
wasn't a hundred percent sure that I was
consciously avoiding the trap of
placebos but I am aware that that that
phrasing this carefully does avoid a
whole spectrum of bad fates and so
anyway to make a long story short I am
curious whether I have misunderstood
what he said about homeopathy or you did
I will have to go back and look but he's
right my rubric for presenting
metaphorical truth does negate the
question of the importance of placebos
because it's a question of behavior not
belief the way I have phrased it mm-hmm
good behavior not belief and then the
end of that first question from Ecco is
how can the mechanism of homeopathy be
compared to vaccines and I would say to
first pass there doesn't appear to be a
mechanism of homeopathy it is entirely
belief and to whatever degree that
belief can change outcomes in some
sectors it therefore has the possibility
of sometimes having an effect but
vaccines are actual biological agents
that are being used to get your immune
system to respond on your behalf and
homeopathy is doing nothing of the sort
yeah the vaccines take fragments of
something or inactivated viruses and
they inject them into your system where
it wrecked your system recognizes them
as hostile and it learns to fight them
in their enfeebled or non viable form
then it's better prepared when you are
challenged with an actual pathogen
rather likely dead viruses that are
being shed by the people who were
infected the Theodore Roosevelt right
yes sorry come on no that's it okay okay
second question from echos second
questions you say that values are
discovered if we agree to kill bed bugs
because of traumatic insemination not
sure that's the phrase intended here but
it is okay okay if we agree to kill
bedbugs because of traumatic
insemination we agree humans hold better
values say bedbugs don't feel pain is
pain a prerequisite for bonding and
consciousness
okay echo some humans have better values
than bedbugs
all right you sure you're not drinking
I have not its water
yeah so I want to understand this
question first of all I think there's a
conflation of things several things
values our values discovered I certainly
don't think I've ever said that we've
talked about the need to navigate to
superior locations superior being
defined by an agreement on the values
that we are trying to reach what would
be the alternative discovered versus
creative well like those that they were
always there and they're being
discovered as opposed to created by
human I think this is an is odd if you I
think there are those for example Sam
Harris who I think sets a high bar in
general people who believe you can
derive the art from the is or limbs
obviously Sam isn't I don't think he's
right as I've told him but nonetheless
you could deduce values only we're
properly connected to is my point would
be why bother if you take people
reasonable people and you query them
about their values what you will find
and I've done this experiment many times
is that in general most people at least
in the West share a large number of
values what they don't share is the
ordering of them that is to say their
priority relative to each other or their
assessment of where we are as a society
with respect to realizing those values
we differ over that but in general what
we all want is pretty similar
and so anyway you don't have to derive
this from an is it probably isn't
possible to derive it from and is and
just not sure there's any value in it
so the question then is we should kill
bedbugs because they infest your house
in your bed and they cause a terrible
rash that's good enough reason for me
not because their values are bad in fact
I can pretty much guarantee you they
don't have values they just they're
little robots that are programmed to do
their bedbug thing as with so many of
echos questions there's we could unpack
it it I think the question itself is so
fractal it has many many layers yeah but
maybe we will move on in order to get
through a few more of these questions so
the last thing echo says is bed bugs
don't feel pain is pain a prerequisite
to bonding and consciousness I don't
know if it's a prerequisite to
consciousness
but I would say but it always does
predate it in evolutions of
consciousness that we see on this planet
yeah
on the other hand the things that you
have listed that contribute to the
likelihood of the evolution of
consciousness are all things that would
require pain to keep you out of damaging
trouble which would require would
suggest therefore that it is that pain
is a prerequisite for consciousness I
wouldn't call it a prerequisite I would
say it always precedes it you know in
the same way yeah so um you know you
have to mm-hmm you have to be born to
feel pain I guess but it you know
prerequisites kind of a it's a it's not
a logical prerequisite as far as I know
yeah but I would say there is an
argument to be made that pain or some
analog of it is a prerequisite to
meaning I wouldn't be surprised if that
was a fair climber so anyway don't know
if that's what you're after okay that's
good I like that
thanks for the podcast this is a
two-part question you're going to read
both of them
thanks for the podcast you've both
earned my trust great thank you
can you more thoroughly address the
reddit article by virologist James do
our PhD which argues for the non lab
emergence theory of the virus Dora
resorts to ad hominem attacks appeals to
Authority and straw man arguments but he
also makes scientific arguments that my
music degree degree has not trained me
to evaluate I believe this is the long
one that we got asked about last time
and that you then what you said about it
last time and I haven't looked at it was
it's super long it appears to engage a
lot of the arguments and that leads you
to suggest that maybe it's it's doing
something right but when you picked a
piece out of it somewhat haphazardly you
found that he wasn't making good sense
so you've now spent just a little bit
more time with it it's been
significantly more timely that's more
I've handed it off to some folks who
know more about it than I do
and I must say it doesn't get better it
gets worse now that said I'm having
trouble remembering the name of the
author I think this is the right paper
but if we were discussing some different
paper then all bets are off but if it's
the one we were asked about last time
well the question there and again I'm
sorry I don't know your name the moment
because of how we're looking at these
can you more thoroughly address the
right article I think this is the
estable that last time I said was an
error an error because it claimed that
the Czar's Cove 2 would show hallmarks
of genetic engineering if it had been
altered and does not show them and it's
wrong on both counts because it wouldn't
necessarily show them people have Ralph
barek for example has demonstrated an
ability to do seamless editing and the
other thing is this virus does show some
evidence but this is actually a good
maybe this is what you're looking for to
say that this virus shows some evidence
of genetic manipulation is not to say
that the evidence is conclusive it is to
say some evidence so I think we've been
tripping over this those of us who've
been discussing this in public which is
to say people say there's no evidence of
and that's just not true there's lots of
evidence and the evidence doesn't all
point in the same direction
so we have to be very careful and we
should frankly be generous with each
other because we all have an interest in
figuring out where this thing came from
we do whether you realize it or not we
just simply do so anyway yeah I think
that paper is full of flaws and I
believe soon we will explore them more
deeply maybe not with respect to that
paper itself but the general arguments
it's its marshalling next question dum
necessary plumber here is it possible
for mosquitos to be a vector for covin I
want to start by addressing the lay up
layout lay up set up face question dum
necessary plumber I assume that that dum
is included here because much of the
white-collar world imagines that those
who do real work that has manifestations
in the physical world art as bright as
those who sit behind desks and work in
cubicles and such and this is of course
a position that we have argued against
stringently forever
not not merely because so many of our
most brilliant students themselves came
from the trades often and not merely
because we both do physical work
ourselves and have learned sometimes the
hard way how difficult much of it is and
how valuable it is and how doing work
that has a manifestation of the physical
world means it's not game ax bull and
therefore you actually know at the end
of it whether or not you've done
something right or wrong whereas so much
of the work that's passing for
intellectual work or at least
white-collar work now has no such
outcome and so you just can't tell and
so those people are more likely to
potentially fool themselves more and
more and more you can't do that if
you're a plumber so let me just start by
start by addressing the idea of a dumb
plumber I don't think it's possible
really
is it possible for mosquitoes to be a
vector for Kovan no I think we have seen
it transmitting in so many places where
there are not mosquitoes at the time of
year where it's transmitting it's
transmitting almost entirely indoors
where mostly people don't have
mosquitoes
you know and vectored vector diseases
just have very different hallmarks to
them and I can't say what they all are
but I would say I would I would I would
put a lot of money on this isn't a
vector disease well we have to do a
little interpretation of what the
question is is it currently vectored by
mosquitoes in any meaningful degree I
think we know it is not okay I can
obviously construct a reductio ad
absurdum where you've coughed on a
mosquito you know so that's conceivable
is it conceivable that it could evolve
to be translated by but could it evolve
to be vector by a mosquito here's what I
won't want to know the first if I became
obsessed with this question the first
thing I would want to do just figure out
whether any coronavirus is being
vectored this way and I don't know
there's certainly so yellow fever is an
RNA virus vector by mosquitos so RNA
virus yes but yellow fever isn't a
corona virus so I would love to know are
there any known corona viruses vector by
mosquito if the answer is no then the
answer to your question is probably not
if the answer is yes then the answer to
your question is could be let's not give
them the opportunity to evolve that
trick
yeah that's not please here's a request
for us to look at something that we
haven't seen yet but I'll just read it
please look at polar 50 forties
fantastic analysis of Tsarskoe B two
sources of the you to blink his points
about evolved versus chimeric origin are
particularly relevant okay are you
familiar with the danger model or danger
I don't know which it is in immunology
which says right there that I at least
don't know it NIH has a great videocast
series by Pauline Matson der which may
or may not be related to this you know
that name um I believe I saw some very
good stuff I couldn't swear that was the
name but I think so um the 'danger model
so here's the problem as I took
you know biology at the University of
Pennsylvania back in 1991 87 baby right
yeah baby you know your freshman it's a
great course did I learn this model that
the model exists yet and have I
forgotten that that's the name of it I
don't know at least don't know it by
that name yep if it's new then probably
we don't know it if it's old then
probably I knew it but I forgotten
that's the name yeah
sorry what time are we at suck 42 okay
let's just we got two more questions
and then I'll switch we got a few more
but let's just do the next two here have
you read any of the work done by David
Deutsch and his take on pop Aryan
epistemology regardless do you think
popper had it right knowledge through
conjecture and criticism not empiricism
that's an interesting characterization
of popper that's not how I would have
characterized it I think I know what is
being alluded to here but it's not it's
not the part of popper that we were
focused on through you know Clube and
such and epistemology when we were in
graduate school yeah and I certainly
never heard in the long discussions that
we had about popper and falsification
and such a desire to throw out
empiricism but I don't know can you
could you go further with us yeah I mean
I would say a popper had it at least
partly right falsification is clearly a
huge step in the right direction
I would doubt he had it completely right
and he certainly didn't all along one of
the most important things and the reason
that he was sort of contentious in our
grad school environment was that he had
initially been kind of an anti
adaptation esteem around later in life
so that's to his credit he saw the power
of this style of thinking and anyway so
I would say loosely speaking I feel pop
Aryan I'm sure I don't subscribe to all
of it
yeah so field Darwinian and I don't
subscribe to every detail but but anyway
yeah did he have it right he advanced
the ball substantially yeah and with
regard to David Deutsch and his take
have read some of the Abdullah's work
but I don't remember his take on popper
particularly yeah if you do me either at
the moment I'm a little leery based on
his multi world stuff but Deutsch is
yeah so anyway not much to say
unfortunately yeah last you questions I
wanted to read here are both ones I'm
not sure that we can do particularly
well on have you any thoughts on Terra
Preta the black birth of the Amazon
thanks as always I don't know what that
is and I don't know if it's possible
that the spelling is throwing me and I
don't know I will look it up I have some
danced yeah what is it it is a kind of
self renewing artificially enriched soil
so it's kind of it's part of a Amazonian
agricultural tradition that goes back a
couple thousand years anyway here's what
what we've done by agriculturalists in
the Amazon long before there were any
people but the original / Indians in the
new world you know who are doing this or
with bioactive techniques like well so
it you know it's reminiscent of what the
Maya were doing in the sense that the
Maya had very sophisticated soil
chemistry at the empirical level what
they understood about what they were
doing and why it worked
we have no idea sure but but in both
cases both the Amazonians and the Maya
Maya less so but we're working with very
poor tropical soils as tropical soils
tend to be except in volcanic zones yep
so they needed to enrich their soil
affair according to be agriculturalists
the Maya in many cases were working with
alluvial soils which are better than
average
but we're still talking about a tropical
alluvial soil and the Amazonians were
obviously working in an environment
which there's a lot of nutrient but it's
not in the soil it's not very deep at
all so anyway these soils were enriched
in a way that as my understanding which
is very superficial is that they are
sort of self renewing and that they're
still sort of functionally findable
still now yeah so anyway amazing right
it's fantastic if the story is anything
like we think it is it's a case of human
beings having made a discovery of some
form that allowed them to alter the
capacity of the Amazon to deliver crops
and that in effect what they've done is
something you know where we would have
trouble reproducing the level of success
on that soil yes we can
drench it in some kind of externally
derived fertilizer but a self renewing
soil would be you know beyond us what
you could do and yet people who didn't
have sophisticated laboratories or a
periodic table or anything we're able to
deduce how to get there and this is the
nature of human beings it's the the
flip-flop between culture and
consciousness and this is the kind of
thing it produces yeah that's great okay
Zak you want to show us questions from
the next live stream okay we are giving
our wonderful 16 year old son one second
has he been upgraded to wonderful yes
yeah actually I made that decision
without asking you you didn't have to
ask you now yeah okay hmm Heather what
is the biggest challenge you witness
Brett to face or overcome Brett what is
the biggest challenge you witness
Heather face or overcome man that's a
big question yeah do we want to try to
answer that now or do you want to save
it for having with the with the promise
that we will try to address it but
save it for I'm cool either way okay
well I guess also the thing about us
looking at this screen is that we're
seeing us like 10 seconds ago that's
super weird it's fine it's fine
I think the the trade-off having to do
with your unique brilliance makes it
difficult for you to meet some of the
expectations of a modern society go on I
know that to be true as as do you yep
and it is not for lack of self awareness
on your part certainly when we first met
when we were in high school you weren't
aware but watching your self awareness
of your own difficulties meeting
expectations that need to be met that
are not simply owners or stupid rise
with with with a rise also in your
ability to overcome that but it's not
commitment with like the rise in your
ability to overcome it hasn't risen as
hasn't gone as fast as your rising
self-awareness so in some ways you're
more evermore frustrated with yourself I
think yeah right yeah and it sucks I
know what I should be doing just can't
make myself doing yeah alright so you
know I'm gonna swap the answer I was
gonna deliver for a better one I think
more insightful we share with me the
other one later
sure nothing that would surprise you but
the thing about Heather is that she was
tremendously introverted and she still
has these instincts but she has
discovered over time that the value that
she can deliver in the world that her
ability to generate things that she
holds
hi NF esteemed to be worth her time has
required her to find skills to function
as an extrovert even though it is not in
her nature at all and in particular you
know I when you first started teaching I
think you were just mortified by
standing in front of the class
yeah you really did and so I watched in
a very short number of years it wasn't
like this was the way things were at the
end of your teaching ever and this was
the way things were all along you having
learned this trick as a teaching
assistant in graduate school but you
managed to induce a kind of desire to
impress you and get your approval in
students that most people if they had
that kind of influence over people would
abuse it or they wouldn't take it
seriously but you used it so carefully
and so honorably in order to get
students to perform at a level that most
of them did not know that they could
perform that it was it was it was
astonishing because you know first of
all people were very frequently your
students were very frequently
intimidated by you and so they would
talk to me about this I some reason they
were less intimidated by me and they
would talk to me no it's absolutely true
they would talk to me about you know
their concerns and if you know if
somebody did something great and you you
know would your feedback was of course
always extensive and you would deliver
this this piece of feedback to them and
they would be just so overjoyed to have
discovered something that was of enough
value to catch your attention in all of
this so anyway my point is you mastered
something that was outside of what even
felt comfortable for you at first and
you know I think you still have this
tension within you but the way you
overcame your own shyness in order to be
able to slam dunk the role of professor
and be the professor everybody everybody
needs and most people who see it know
enough to walk
that right that was stunning and I have
to tell you among the things that makes
me absolutely the most livid about what
happened in Evergreen was that they
dared to do this to you after you had
risen to the the top of this this role
where you know students adored you and
they were so right to do it because what
you were doing was so good for them and
that these people treated that was such
a disrespect was just despicable
absolutely despicable
that's an amazing answer thank you
it's all true and you know what there's
not a student that was in your class he
wouldn't back me up how about this for
the next unknown virus offer $100,000 to
people to get infected and live on site
of the infection clears sample-sized a
thousand in two weeks we would have an
estimate of the death rate I love ideas
like this I don't think we need it and I
don't really want us to engage in this
kind of thing because we don't need it
but I do I think we need to start
thinking like this but it it would give
us it would give us more than just a
death rate right it would give us other
clues to how it progressed and people
who didn't die and how people recover it
and such but it would mostly give us a
death rate at a particular moment in
time and as we've talked about as you
specifically talked about in the last
last two minutes we've been talking
about for many of them the fact is that
the reason one of the big reasons this
is so hard to pin down is that it is
rapidly evolving and so that would give
us a snapshot of its early its early
evolution especially if it's an emerging
virus that hasn't known humans before
now that that that first moment that
it's in humans is not necessarily going
to look like the moment three months
later or six months later or a year
there yeah so in principle something
like this I prefer in the case of
infectious disease that we find
good natural experiments so that we
don't end up confronting the ethical
dilemma of effectively paying people to
suffer harm on our behalf and things
like that which you know that people
sign up for clinical trials and stuff so
it's not like that's unheard of but
anyway there's a slippery slope here and
I would like not to step so far on to it
that we end up you know a crumpled heap
at the bottom yeah I have followed you
since Evergreen debacle thank you what
do you do when you are weary hmm well a
number of things
yesterday I had a particularly agonizing
and horrifying day trying to learn new
tax software and get our various threads
financial threads into a single coherent
mass and it was not successful and I
mean I was literally in tears at times
which doesn't happen very often
there's a point in the middle of the day
where you were flirting with the concept
of Anarchy that's rarer than tears for
me yeah yeah
and at some point hmm I don't know six
six thirty you came into I was working
you know papers of computer all around
me and just you know my head in my hands
like oh my god and you said we're going
outside and it was a gross day here it
was cool and I mean from May it was dark
and gray and a little windy and a little
bit rainy but we live in a beautiful
place we live in the forest and we've
made it more beautiful during lockdown
by a lot but getting rid of a lot of the
invasive plants and planting a lot of
things and you know I said to you
standing out there just you know even
just for five minutes I said if I had to
choose if I had to choose between ever
being able to be outside again and never
being able to be on a computer again the
choice is so obvious even though it
would interfere with my ability to do
what I want to do in the world and be
creative and productive in the way that
I need to so being outside in nature is
is a big
sir - what what we both do and we're
worried there are many other answers
yeah I'm not sure how much I relate to
the concept of being wearing it you know
I did there's certain things that just I
know they exist it's not like I haven't
felt them but um but they just don't
crop up that much and you know there's a
lot of times when I'm just not
productive the way I should be I know
what I should be producing and I'm not
producing it but but that said I do feel
like we've chosen to live in a way that
that there's a lot that's
thought-provoking and sometimes being
lost in thought and then finding
something interesting and sparking a
discussion and seeing where it goes
that that process is productive over the
long haul even if you couldn't measure
the productivity in a given day or a
given week so anyway I've learned to
trust that and it's amazing how often
the the answer you've been looking for
comes out of the blue after months
sometimes years of searching in what
feels like an unproductive way and I
know those two things are not
disconnected so the searching doesn't
feel productive but it is productive
therefore you should hack the system so
that you can feel productive with it
without requiring yourself to deliver
evidence because eventually the thing
you know just emerges in a psycho
well that was worth it good does being
left-handed say anything about humans
either psychologically maybe
physiologically psychologically isn't a
thing we are so I'm going to go with I'm
gonna start over again and insert my
interpretation of what this word is does
being left-handed say anything about
humans either physiologically or
psychologically I love you guys thanks
so another topic about which I could
talk endlessly we as vertebrates have
lateralization which means we have were
bilaterally symmetrical and we aren't
perfectly symmetrical at the
brain level and therefore at at the
appendicular skeleton level so all of us
and all of us humans have not just a
dominant hand but also dominant foot to
dominate ear dominant eye and once you
establish what your dominant hand is
it's likely that you are the same
dominant foot and ear and eye but not
totally clear and so what what would be
the value and having one be dominant
over the other well it's a kind of
specialization right but then why
shouldn't everyone in the population
just have exactly the same
specialization it would certainly make
it easier for the left handers myself
included if I didn't always have to find
a different spatula different pair of
scissors and you know you know find when
we're sharing cheese together I have to
switch it around to be able to access
the you know the correct end of the
cheese etc but at a population level
having roughly 10% across all
populations where it's ever been looked
at which is to say pretty much all human
populations have been looked at roughly
10% of the population being left-handed
as opposed to right-handed allows for a
different kind of approach to situations
and not just a physical approach like oh
I'm trying to climb a tree and all the
lawyers before me couldn't get there but
the left-hander has a different
different vantage on it but also just a
different a different mental approach to
different like momentum from mental
rotation to just mental gymnastics but a
4 o'clock gymnastics is is differently
allowed by a left-handed brain it's also
true that left-handers are less
specialized with regard to
lateralization that we tend to have
larger more connected corpus collosum z'
which means that our left and right
hemispheres are more connected of course
the trade-off being that it's harder to
get things past one hemisphere with the
other and perhaps harder to find total
utter focus and go super deep that you
know it's maybe more of a generalist
paradigm so there's a lot more to be
said there but tantalizing fact you tell
me if I have it wrong enlarged corpus
callosum accompanies the condition of
being female
being gay and male and being left-handed
am i correct yes with the caveat that so
this is something I used to always say
in my classes and occasionally I'd get
so it's not just gay and male just
homosexual so females homosexuals and
left-handers all are understood as I
used to say to my classes a lot to have
larger corpus callosum than than men
straight people or right-handers and you
know in almost every class I'd get
someone going you know I got all three
but it's a it's not better it's
different you know it's it's just a
different way of being that is better in
some situations but not others and when
I looked into it recently I think that I
remember that the data are around women
was actually a little bit more nuanced
than it seemed because of course like
all of these things in a complex body
like a human body corpus callosum
doesn't have strict boundaries and so
exactly what you're measuring is is not
totally clear and if you measure it one
way it seems like females have slightly
larger corpus callosum than men but if
you measure it maybe a slightly more
standard way that difference disappeared
so I'm not sure that it totally holds up
and it seems to maybe so the data Iran
women is harder to understand and smells
better is that what you're saying it's
exactly what I said okay
perfect yeah is virus RNA more
information intensive than human DNA
referring to non-coding DNA if that is
the case does it affect how viruses
evolve compared to same mammals
information intensive sure hard
information intensive means I think what
it means is less room for noisy stuff
and that's probably true the fact of
just because it's more constrained by
size yeah is that why you say it's
probably true yeah at the cost of wasted
spaces is higher relative to the total
that said junk DNA is a concept that I'm
proud to say never made a widow sense to
me
they don't this person doesn't say
chocolates right noncoding right yeah so
there is non-coding stuff that it still
contains information telomere would be a
great example so it's a little hard to
evaluate your question because there may
be more of that stuff in let's say
vertebrate DNA then there is in viral
DNA because maybe more of the viral DNA
is protein coding or there abouts so
anyway it's hard to compare the two I
would say probably there's more room in
vertebrates for noisy stuff and
inefficiency and so you might expect
more of it and yes this would have an
effect on evolution because what it
means is nonsynonymous mutations would
be more likely to be disruptive so
anyway you might expect something like
that to alter the rate of evolution
under certain circumstances or maybe all
of them so yes broad-brush I think
you're on the right track how to say it
specifically I don't know and I'm sure
there are people who are expert in this
exact question and we're not done so we
are at an hour and 10 we are I think all
right well we have arrived at the end of
the Q&A wow that flew by yeah all right
so this has been excellent we will
return on Saturday May 23rd with a
Evergreen themed retrospective special
live stream Dark Horse podcast and that
sort of thing so look forward to it xxx
Pacific 12:30 Pacific so like subscribe
comment hit notify be well stay safe and
we will see you on Saturday
you